#35, Odai Street, Veeman Nagar,

Puducherry. Pin: 605009

Cell: +91-9003402626

E-Mail: avichandran@outlook.com

Links: www.linkedin.com/in/avichandran90bioinfo

Avinash R

MPhil, Bioinformatics

Summary

Enthusiastic Bioinformatician eager to contribute to team success through hard work, attention to details and 5+ Years of Industrial Experience in Genomics research. Motivated to learn, grow and excel in Science. Actively looking for a suitable position to contribute my knowledge of

Work History

Bioinformatics in research.

✓ QA Engineer (Bioinformatics), November 2021 to February 2023

Pieriandx/Velsera Pvt, Ltd., Pune, Maharashtra, India

 Review technical design documents, requirements documents, and specifications to provide timely and insightful feedback.

 Assess requirements in collaboration with teams (such as SMEs, developers and product managers).

• Create detailed, comprehensive, and well-structured test plans and test cases.

• Estimate, prioritize, plan, and coordinate testing activities.

• Design and execute automation scripts using open-source tools.

• Identify, record, document thoroughly and track bugs.

• Perform thorough regression testing when bugs are resolved.

• Investigate the causes of non-conforming software and train users to implement solutions.

• Track quality assurance metrics, like defect densities and open defect counts.

• Develop and apply testing processes for new and existing products to meet client needs.

• Create QSI and SDLC documents and getting them reviewed by peers and QMS.

✓ Senior Scientific Analyst, July 2020 to May 2021

Genotypic Technologies Pvt, Ltd., Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

- Analyzing Next Generation Sequencing Data of Transcriptome, miRNA, Degradome, Metagenomics, Whole Genome and Methyl-Seq.
- Exploring new tools and improving analysis pipelines for breaking down and analyzing complex data.
- Evaluated potential subject participants to assess suitability for planned studies.
- Collaborated with Scientist to identify relevant.

✓ <u>Junior Scientific Analyst</u>, January 2019 to June 2020

Genotypic Technologies Pvt, Ltd., Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

- Analyzed Next Generation Sequencing Data of Transcriptome, miRNA, Degradome and Metagenomics.
- Built and improved analysis pipelines for breaking down and analyzing complex data.
- Worked with Linux, Perl and R to manage project requirements.
- Performed statistical, qualitative, and quantitative analysis.

✓ Bioinformatics Analyst, October 2017 to December 2018

Arraygen Technologies Pvt. Ltd., Pune, Maharashtra, India

- Taught NGS data Analysis to the clients on information compiled from public resources and research materials.
- Handled projects on Transcriptome, small RNA, Metagenomics and R for the Clients.

Publication

Deshpande SS, Nemani H, Arumugam G, **Ravichandran A**, Balasinor NH. High-fat diet-induced and genetically inherited obesity differentially alters DNA methylation profile in the germline of adult male rats. Clin Epigenetics. 2020 Nov 19;12(1):179. doi: 10.1186/s13148-020-00974-7. PMID: 33213487; PMCID: PMC7678167.

Education

✓ Masters in Philosophy Bioinformatics - August 2017

Department Of Bioinformatics, Alagappa University, Karaikudi

- Thesis: Discovery of potent inhibitors of Dengue Envelope protein through E-Pharmacophore Screening and Drug Repurposing Approach
- Graduated with 7.66 CGPA

✓ Master of Science Bioinformatics - August 2013

Centre For Bioinformatics, Pondicherry University, Puducherry

- Thesis: Molecular Evolutionary study of KISS1 in Mammals
- Graduated with 5.8 CGPA

✓ Bachelor of Science Bioinformatics - April 2011

Achariya Arts and Science College, Puducherry

• Graduated with 67.3%

✓ Higher Secondary - April 2008

Vaillankani Matric. Higher Secondary School, Puducherry

• With 53.5%

✓ High School / SSLC -March 2006

Govt. High School, Thattanchavady, Puducherry

With 65.8%

Areas of Interest

• Next Generation Sequencing Analysis

Practical Experiences

- Drug designing
- Next Generation Sequence Analysis RNA-Seq, miRNA-Seq, Methyl-Seq, Chip-Seq, Metagenomics, Microarray, WGS.

Software and Tools

- Phylogenetic Tools: MEGA, CLUSTALW, Philip.
- Databases: UCSC Genome Broswer, NCBI, Uniprot, KEGG, JGI

- NGS:
 - RNA-Seq: FastQC, Cutadapt, Bowtie, Cufflinks, Samtools, Tophat, HISAT2, String Tie, Aspli, Astalavista, BWA, DESeq
 - Methyl-Seq: Homer, bismark, Methylkit
 - Chip-Seq: Chipseeker.
 - Metagenomics: Qiime , Centrifuge, Blast+
 - MicroArray: Affy, DAVID, G:Profiler
 - WGS: MaSurca, Spades, MiniMap, BWA
- Docker
- AWS

Programming Languages

- Perl
- R
- Python

Skills

- R and Perl proficiency
- Python scripting
- Shell scripting
- Linux expertise
- MS Office

- Code troubleshooting
- Data collection and analysis
- Software and system modification
- Communications
- Work independently

Declaration

I hereby declare that the above information is correct to the best of my knowledge.

Avinash R